John Margetts Bull Papers
John Margetts Bull Papers
1849-1877
Bull, John Margetts.
1.5 linear ft.
Biographical material and writings (speeches, reviews, essays, sermons, etc) of the American clergyman.
2642145
Biographical History
John Margetts Bull (1812?-1897?) was an American Methodist clergyman.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Margetts Bull Papers consist of biographical material and photocopies of writings by Bull, including addresses, book reviews, essays, lectures, notes, reviews, and sermons. The latter constitute the bulk of the collection. They are of course religious in character, but also refer to current events and social questions of the time, such as a typhoid epidemic, the Great Rebellion (Civil War), and the characteristics of a good teacher.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has the papers of numerous clergymen as well as the records of a number of churches. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; New York State; Bull, John Margetts.; Clergy -- United States.; Methodist Church -- Clergy.; New York (State) -- Manners and customs.; Book reviews.; Essays.; Lectures.; Notes (documents); Sermons.; Clergy.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Marian Bull Wheeler, February 1988. Given in honor of her father, Charles King Bull.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Addresses
    - Mental Power, 1858? (Box 1)
    - (Untitled). Sodus, Winter, 1845-1846 (Box 1)
  - Bible Class Lessons
    - #1 On the existence and attributes of God (Box 1)
    - #2 Creation, 1856 (Box 1)
    - #3 The Flood (Box 1)
  - Book Review
    - "Philosophy of the plan of Salvation" (Box 1)
  - Essays
    - Abrahamic covenant (Box 1)
    - On ancient religious festivals, 1869? (Box 1)
    - Birth of Christ, 1849 (Box 1)
    - The Church, the past, the present, and the future (Box 1)
    - Church Saving (Box 1)
    - Conflict of antagonistic principles (Box 1)
    - Duties of members of the M.E. Church towards their pastors (Box 1)
    - Essay on posthumous influence (Box 1)
    - On the gradual development of religious truth, 1861 (Box 1)
    - History of the Prophets (Box 1)
    - History of the Prophets, cont (Box 1)
    - The human mind (Box 1)
    - "I know thy work" (Box 1)
    - Lord's Supper (Box 1)
    - Lost soul (Box 1)
    - Moral agency of man, 1849 (Box 1)
    - On sacrifice, 1857; 1861,; 1866,; 1869 (Box 1)
    - On the best means of promoting a revival of religion (Box 1)
    - The responsibilities of teachers (Box 1)
    - A shadow of things to come (Box 1)
    - Worldly amusements versus the Church (Box 1)
    - Untitled, 3 items (Box 1)
  - Lectures
    - The ideal and the actual (Box 1)
    - Temperance, 1850 (Box 1)
    - Lecture #3, On Bible chronology, 1867; 1868 (Box 1)
    - Lecture #14, Israel and her judges (Box 1)
    - Lecture #15, Israel and her judges, cont (Box 1)
    - Bible Lecture #16, Israel and her judges, cont (Box 1)
    - #17 Scripture history: Samuel and the Kingdom, 1869 (Box 1)
    - #18 Saul and David., 1870 (Box 1)
    - #19 David., 1870 (Box 1)
    - Lecture #20 Solomon, 1870 (Box 1)
    - Lecture #21 Division of the Kingdom, 1870 (Box 1)
    - Lecture #22 Kingdom of Israel, 1870 (Box 1)
    - #23 Kingdom of Judah, 1870? (Box 1)
  - Legal documents
    - Constitution of Canandaigua District Ministerial Association (Box 1)
  - Missionary address
    - A world converted to Christ (Box 1)
  - Notes
    - Early usages with respect to the Lord's Supper (Box 1)
    - Testimonies of Saints (Box 1)
  - Obituary
    - Andrews, Herman (Box 1)
    - Rev. Ira Fairbanks. Died, Benton Center, Yates County, N.Y., May 31, 1857 (Box 1)
    - Lisk, Elizabeth (Box 1)
  - Reviews
    - Methodist Quarterly Review, April (Box 1)
  - Scripture lessons
    - Untitled, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Sermons
    - Advantages of a return to the Almighty (Box 1)
    - Advantages of retirement for religious purposes, or, a plea for Camp Meetings (Box 1)
    - Advent of Christ (Box 1)
    - Agony of Christ (Box 1)
    - All for Jesus, 1869 (Box 1)
    - Amazing love of God as displayed in the high priveleges (sic) and perogatives [sic] of God's people (Box 1)
    - Assimilation to the Divine image, 1870; 1871,; 1872,; 1873 (Box 1)
    - Atonement with its glorious results (Box 1)
    - The beneficial results of a national annual Thanksgiving (Box 1)
    - Bondage of sin (Box 1)
    - The brevity of time (Box 1)
    - Christ Jesus the only source and dispenser of the blessings of salvation (Box 1)
    - Christ stilling the tempest (Box 1)
    - Christ the sacrificial offering for human guilt (Box 1)
    - Christian aims and efforts (Box 1)
    - The Christian Church, the agent in the World's conversion, 1855 (Box 1)
    - Christian minister's closing act for his people (Box 1)
    - The Christian ministry, 1859; 1861 (Box 1)
    - Christian Unity, 1866; 1870 (Box 1)
    - Christian watchword (Box 1)
    - Christ's second Advent (Box 1)
    - The Death of Saints Precious (Box 1)
    - Death of the soul (Box 1)
    - Deluge (Box 1)
    - Divine and human agencies cooperative in promoting the best interests of the race, 1869 (Box 1)
    - Divine and human agencies cooperative in promoting the best interests of the race. (rewritten), 1880 (Box 1)
    - Divine expectations not realized (Box 2)
    - The Divine hand in public calamities (on the occasion of the great fire at Chicago, Oct 8, 1871) (Box 2)
    - Divine help in time of earthly sorrow (Box 2)
    - Divine longsuffering, 1869; 1870,; 1873 (Box 2)
    - Divine support in the time of trouble (Box 2)
    - Duty of the Church in respect to the erring and the disobedience (Box 2)
    - Duty of the Church with regard to children (Box 2)
    - Duty of the Church with respect to education (Box 2)
    - Duty of the hour (Box 2)
    - Entire consecration to God accepted and ratified (Box 2)
    - Faith an absolute condition to the reception of the blessings of salvation (Box 2)
    - Forgiveness (Box 2)
    - God pleading His own cause (Box 2)
    - God the Christian's Rock (Box 2)
    - God's witnesses, 1871; 1872,; 1875,; 1877? (Box 2)
    - Golden rule as applicable to our duty with respect to missions (Box 2)
    - The Gospel the Wisdom of God (Box 2)
    - Grateful joy of the soul that has Jehovah for its salvation (Box 2)
    - The harmony existing between the Divine, and human government, 1864 (Box 2)
    - Heart iniquity and effectual barrier between the soul and God (Box 2)
    - The heinous nature & effects of sin, 1872 (Box 2)
    - Historical sermon #1 - Scriptural characters: Adam, 1860; 1861 (Box 2)
    - Historical sermon #4 - The life and times of Noah (Box 2)
    - Historical sermon #5 - Job, 1861; 1863,; 1865,; 1868,; 1871,; 1874 (Box 2)
    - Historical sermon #6 - Abraham (Box 2)
    - Holy Eucharist (Box 2)
    - Hope of the Soul (Box 2)
    - Human sorrow alleviated (on the occasion of the death of 3 persons by small-pox), 1869 (Box 2)
    - The imperatively specific and religious duty, 1858; 1860 (Box 2)
    - Individuality of human duty (Box 2)
    - Individuality of human responsibility (Box 2)
    - Infinite contrast between present and external things (Box 2)
    - Inseparable connection of the Divine Promise with our duty in world's conversion (Box 2)
    - Intemperance and the duty of the hour (Box 2)
    - Jesus Christ is the only source of the blessings of salvation (Box 2)
    - Justification, its high and exalted character (Box 2)
    - Lean hand. (Ch. Adv.), March 11, 1869 (Box 2)
    - (To the Sunday School) The Letter "S" (Box 2)
    - (Notes) Levi (Box 2)
    - Light from the sanctuary on dark and mysterious providences (Box 2)
    - Loss and gain (Box 2)
    - Lost soul (Box 2)
    - Lore of Christ a divine force (Box 2)
    - Marks of true discipleship to Christ, 1872; 1873,; 1874 (Box 2)
    - Moral contrast (Box 2)
    - National advantages arising from the possession of the Divine Oracles (Box 2)
    - National affairs, 1861 (Box 2)
    - Nature and office work of the Holy Spirit (Box 2)
    - Neutrality towards the Church of God impossible (Box 2)
    - Noble Bereans (Box 2)
    - Of Angels, 1869 (Box 2)
    - Office and work of Christ (Box 2)
    - Old paths (Box 2)
    - On Baptism (Box 2)
    - On Church polity, 1855 (Box 2)
    - On Conscience (Box 2)
    - On death (Box 2)
    - On prophecy, 1857 (Box 2)
    - On sacred song (Box 2)
    - On the death of Albert H. Stacy who was slain in battle, Sept.13, 1862 (Box 2)
    - On the due observance of the Sabbath (Box 2)
    - On the occasion of the fall of Richmond, 1865 (Box 2)
    - Opposite views of God (Box 2)
    - The perfect Christian, 1876 (Box 2)
    - Practical atheism (Box 2)
    - Praise for national blessings (Box 2)
    - Praise for national mercies (Box 2)
    - Prayer (Box 2)
    - Premature judging of things mysterious (Box 2)
    - Prime requirement (Box 2)
    - Psychology of conversion (Box 2)
    - Race for glory (Box 2)
    - Relation of the Sunday School to the church and the world (Box 2)
    - The repentance of the Ninevites (Box 2)
    - Resurrection of Christ (Box 2)
    - Returning to God (Box 2)
    - Right - improvement of God-given talents (Box 2)
    - Sabbath (Box 2)
    - Scripture biography #7: scenes in the life of Jacob, 1866; 1867,; 1868,; 1872,; 1874 (Box 2)
    - Scripture biography #8: Life of Joseph (Box 2)
    - Scripture biography #10: Moses, 1869; 1874 (Box 2)
    - Scripture biography #11 Moses, cont (Box 2)
    - Self abasement before God (Box 2)
    - Self conservation to God (Box 2)
    - Self-examination (Box 3)
    - Self-humiliation before God (Box 3)
    - Self-sacrifice for others' benefits (Box 3)
    - Sermon of baptism (rewritten), July 1864 (Box 3)
    - Sermon on the Trinity (Box 3)
    - Spiritual Armory (Box 3)
    - Temperance sermon, 1854 (Box 3)
    - Temperance sermon (Box 3)
    - Thanksgiving sermon - The beneficial results of a national annual Thanksgiving, 1867; 1870,; 1873,; 1874 (Box 3)
    - Thanksgiving sermon - God for the right: a praise for national blessings, 1863 (Box 3)
    - Thanksgiving sermon - Our country - its prosperity, its sins & its future prospects, 1852 (Box 3)
    - Thanksgiving sermon - Rebellion vanquished - Praise to God or/for National Deliverance, 1865 (Box 3)
    - Thanksgiving sermon - The true element of national prosperity, 1858; 1860 (Box 3)
    - Thanksgiving sermon - The true principles of national prosperity, 1856 (Box 3)
    - Time in its relation to humanity (Box 3)
    - Trial of faith (Box 3)
    - The true national fast, with its attendant happy consequences. April 30, 1863 (Box 3)
    - True remedy for troubled times (Box 3)
    - Truth (Box 3)
    - Twelve meanings of the term Xapls-Grace (Box 3)
    - Unaccepted service (Box 3)
    - Unaccomplished purposes (Box 3)
    - Unspeakable gift (Box 3)
    - Uses and ends of Holy Scripture (Box 3)
    - Vigilance against moral evil (Box 3)
    - Untitled, 8 items (Box 3)